Guide to the Ruth Wilson Collection on Human Rights and Social Work TAM.342
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Ruth Wilson Collection on Human Rights and Social Work
1958-2005
1983-2004
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Wilson, Ruth
TAM.342
44.92 Linear Feet in 85 manuscript boxes, 1 flat box, 3 oversized flat boxes, and 4 folders in a shared oversized flat box
19 Megabytes in 19 computer files
4 audiocassette
The Committee for International Human Rights Inquiry (CIHRI) was a social worker driven volunteer organization opposed to human rights violations globally. Social worker Ruth Wilson served as a founder, secretary, and coordinator for CIHRI. The Ruth Wilson Collection of Human Rights and Social Work Records (1958-2005) is comprised of materials created by organizations including the Committee for International Human Rights Inquiry (CIHRI), the International Federation of Social Workers (IFSW), the National Association of Social Workers (NASW), Amnesty International, the United Nations (UN), and more -- all of which were collected by Ruth Wilson. Materials consist of correspondence, research materials, administrative paperwork, conference materials, newsletters, photographs, news clippings, speeches, publications, and brochures. The collection also contains Wilson's personal research materials related to her areas of interests including Marxism, U.S. politics, healthcare reform, unions, Bertha Capen Reynolds, and social work education.
Biographical Note
Ruth Wilson was a social worker and human rights advocate who lived and worked in New York City. In 1974, she and fellow social workers Sol Gorelick, Phyllis Grunauer, and Celia Wolksy founded the Committee for Chilean Inquiry in response to alleged human rights violations in Chile following a 1973 military coup. In 1990, the Committee for Chilean Inquiry changed its name to the Committee for International Human Rights Inquiry (CIHRI). Throughout her membership, Wilson served as both secretary and coordinator of CIHRI. Wilson was involved in other professional organizations including the National Association of Social Workers (NASW) and the International Federation of Social Workers (IFSW).
Wilson's personal and professional interests included, but were not limited to, the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA), American politics, the Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism (a subset of the Communist Party USA), the American healthcare system, domestic violence, Marxism, unions, the LGBTQIA community, racism, discrimination, women's rights, Native American rights, Bertha Capen Reynolds, and Karen Silkwood.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into three series by topic and two sub-series:
Series I: Committee for International Human Rights Inquiry (CIHRI), 1973-2005
Sub-series I.A: Administrative Files, 1974-2003
Sub-series I.B: Topic Files, 1973-2005
Series II: Affiliated Human Rights and Social Work Organizations, 1974-2005
Series III: Research Files, 1958-2004
Within each series, the materials have been grouped thematically and arranged alphabetically.
Scope and Contents
The Ruth Wilson Collection of Human Rights and Social Work Records (1976-2005) is comprised of materials created by organizations including the Committee for International Human Rights Inquiry (CIHRI), the International Federation of Social Workers (IFSW), the National Association of Social Workers (NASW), and the United Nations (UN) – all of which were collected by Ruth Wilson.
The overarching theme of the collection is human rights, human rights violations, and advocacy on behalf of victims of human rights violations. This is reflected in both Sub-series I.B: Topic Files and Series II: Affiliated Human Rights and Social Work Organizations. These series highlight human rights violations in countries including Guatemala, Chile, the Philippines, Israel, Palestine, and South Africa. They also focus upon human rights violations against specific individuals including Olga Gonzalez, Mumia Abu-Jamal, Rula Abu Duhou, Phyllis Coard, Shirley Gunn, Rigoberta Menchu Tum, and Benedict Topin. These subjects are documented through newspaper and magazine clippings; correspondence between human rights advocacy organizations, social workers, and government officials; flyers, posters, and newsletters; conference materials and speeches; petitions, press statements and government reports about human rights conditions globally; journal articles and informational pamphlets; and fact books providing background context about specific countries, individuals, and subjects.
The collection also provides an overview of the administrative aspects of CIHRI, NASW, and IFSW. Documents include membership lists, correspondence, election materials, financial records, historical overviews, meeting materials, conference materials, and newsletters and provide insight on how these organizations operated.
In addition to materials related to human rights, Series III: Research Materials contains Wilson's personal research files related to her interests including, but not limited to the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA), American politics, the Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism (a subset of the Communist Party USA), the American healthcare system, domestic violence, Marxism, unions, the LGBTQIA community, racism, discrimination, women's rights, Native American rights, Bertha Capen Reynolds, and Karen Silkwood.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated by Ruth H. Wilson on behalf of the Committee for International Human Rights Inquiry (CHIRI) in 2005. The accession number associated with this gift is 2005.027.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns. Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted.
Related Materials
Sol Gorelick Papers (WAG.019)
Human rights.; Human rights advocacy.; New York (N.Y.).; Human rights -- Philippines.; Human rights -- Middle East.; Correspondence.; Human rights -- Guatemala.; Human rights -- Chile; Research notes.; Articles.; Newsletters.; Women's rights.; Economics.; Social work.; Photographs.; Audiocassettes.; Memorandums.; Conference proceedings; Financial records; Posters.; Minutes (administrative records); North American Free Trade Agreement (1992 December 17); United States -- Politics and government; Human rights -- Indonesia.; Human rights -- Central America; Human rights -- El Salvador; Human rights -- Haïti.; Apartheid -- South Africa.; Human rights -- Cuba.; Human rights -- Colombia; Human rights -- Indonesia; Human rights -- United States; LGBTQIA; Wilson, Ruth; Committee for International Human Rights Inquiry; National Association of Social Workers; Amnesty International; United Nations; International Federation of Social Workers; Gonzalez, Olga; Abu-Jamal, Mumia; Duhou, Rula Abu; Coard, Phyllis; Gunn, Shirley; Menchú, Rigoberta; Benedict Topin; Reynolds, Bertha Capen, 1885-1978; Silkwood, Karen, 1946-1974; Committees of Correspondence for Democracy and Socialism
- Series I: Committee for International Human Rights Inquiry Records (CIHRI), 1973-2005; 1983-2003; 29.59 Linear Feet in 54 manuscript boxes, 2 flat boxes, and 3 oversized flat boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series I focuses upon the activities of the Committee for International Human Rights Inquiry (CIHRI), which was named the Committee for Chilean Inquiry prior to 1990.
  Materials in this series include correspondence between human rights advocacy organizations, social workers, CIHRI members, and government officials; administrative documents including meeting materials, financial reports, memorandum, and membership lists; brochures and flyers advertising fundraising events; newspaper clippings and articles about human rights violations domestically and internationally; petitions, press statements and speeches; and research materials about specific countries, the types of human rights issues occurring in those countries, and specific individuals. This series also contains three audio cassettes focused upon Palestinian political prisoners in Israel, as well as digital copies of CIHRI membership lists.
  Together, the materials in this series provide a detailed overview of how CIHRI operated, the types of groups CIHRI advocated on behalf of, the geographic regions they focused on, and the types of activities they engaged in.
  Arrangement
  This series is divided into two sub-series: Administrative Files and Topic Files. Materials have been grouped geographically and/or thematically, when possible, and then arranged alphabetically.
  Historical Note
  The Committee for International Human Rights Inquiry (CIHRI) was established in 1974 by social workers Ruth Wilson, Sol Gorelick, Phyllis Grunauer, and Celia Wolksy. Originally called the Committee for Chilean Inquiry, Wilson and her colleagues formed the committee in response to alleged human rights violations in Chile that followed a military coup in 1973. In 1990, the organization changed its name to CIHRI to reflect its mission to protect those subjected to human rights violations globally. CIHRI advocated for all victims of human rights violations and focused on the rights of social service workers and human rights monitors.
  CIHRI members vocalized their opposition to human rights violations and support of victims through letter-writing campaigns to government officials, fundraising events, and public workshops designed to raise awareness about human rights violations in specific countries. They also hosted public workshops focused on social work and human rights education.
  - Sub-Series IA: Administrative Files, 1974-2003; 7.44 Linear Feet in 17 manuscript boxes; 19 Megabytes in 19 computer files
    This sub-series focuses upon the administrative activities of CIHRI and provides an overview of CIHRI's history, organizational structure, activities, funding, and membership. Materials found in this sub-series include both digital and paper membership lists, correspondence, financial records, by-laws, meeting minutes, flyers, newsletters, public workshop materials, history fact sheets, copies of CIHRI's mission statement, and documents that describe about CIHRI's reorganization and name change in 1990.
    - Administrative Files, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - By Laws, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - "Chipping Away at Repression", 1988-1990 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1981-1998 (Box 11, Folder 6, Box 12)
    - Correspondence -- Barbara Weatherspoon, 1987 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence -- Brinton Lykes, 1986 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence -- Bryn Mawr College, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence -- Current Events, 2001 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence -- Fundraising, 1984-1998 (Box 13, Folder 5-8, Box 14, Folder 1-3)
    - Correspondence -- International Federation of Social Workers (IFSW), 1988-1995 (Box 14, Folder 4-5)
    - Correspondence -- Joseph Wronka, 1993, 1998 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence -- Marilyn Moch, 2003 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence -- National Association of Social Workers (NASW), 1987-1994 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence -- Nicole Walden, 2002-2003 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence -- Stephen Lewis (Local 509, SEIU), 1994 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence -- Volunteers, 1988 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence -- Yanino Davila, 1985 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Financial Records, 1983-2001 (Box 18, Folder 5, Box 19, Folder 1-3)
    - General, 1979-2002 (Box 19, Folder 4-7)
    - Handouts and Bulletins, 1974-1997 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - History, Fact Sheets, Reorganization, and Name Change, 1990, 1994, 2001-2002 (Box 25, Folder 6-7)
    - Human Rights Education, Workshops, Conference, and Case Studies, 1984-1996 (Box 26, Folder 1-4)
    - Meeting Materials, 1988-2001 (Box 33, Folder 2-6, Box 34)
    - Membership, 1990-1998; cuid43035 (Box 35, Folder 1-2, Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_342_ER_1)
    - National Association of Social Workers (NASW) Collaboration, 1993-1994 (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - Newsletters, 1986-2002 (Box 35, Folder 5-6, Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Photographs, 1988-1993 (Box 42, Folder 6)
  - Sub-Series IB: Topic Files, 1973-2005; 27.44 Linear Feet in 49 manuscript boxes, 2 flat boxes, and 3 oversized flat boxes
    This sub-series focuses upon specific topics of interest to CIHRI. Human rights violations in countries including Guatemala, El Salvador, Chile, Cuba, the Philippines, Colombia, Iraq, Israel, Palestine, Korea, Puerto Rico, Grenada, South Africa, Malaysia, and Myanmar are documented within this sub-series. Similarly, specific human rights campaigns for individuals including Olga Gonzalez, Mumia Abu-Jamal, Rula Abu Duhou, Phyllis Coard, Shirley Gunn, Rigoberta Menchu Tum, and Benedict Topin are also documented here. In addition to human rights cases, CIHRI's views on topics including global warming, unions, immigration, the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA), the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT), Native American rights, and women's rights are also found within this series.
    These topic files contain newspaper and magazine clippings; petitions and correspondence; CIHRI flyers, posters, and newsletters; and factbooks, journal articles, informational pamphlets, and brochures providing background context about certain countries, individuals, and subjects. Three audiocassette tapes focused upon Palestinian political prisoners in Israel can also be found within this sub-series.
    The file "Guatemala (Contains Graphic Images)" contains visual depictions of deceased individuals who were victims of torture.
    - American Orthopsychiatric Association, 1980-1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Brazil, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Central America, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Chile, 1973-1993 (Box 5, Folder 2-6, Box 6, Box 7, Box 8, Box 9)
    - Chile, 1973-1993 (Box 10, Folder 1-5, Box 86, Folder 1, Box 87, Folder 1-3, Box Shared Tamiment 171, Folder 7)
    - Chile -- Ambassador's Visit to United Nations, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Chile -- Chilean Women's Needlework, undated (Box 89)
    - Chile -- Detained Physicians, 1983-1985 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Chile -- Easter Island, 1983-1985 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Chile -- Fermin Montes Garcia, 1984-1985 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Chile and Guatemala, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Chile -- Jose Manuel Parada Maluenda, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Chile and Malaysia, 1987-1988 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Colombia, 1991-1992 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Cuba, 1990-2002 (Box 15, Folder 6-7, Box 16, Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Cuba -- Elian Gonzalez, 2000 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Detained Social Workers, 1988-1992 (Box 17, Folder 3-4)
    - East Timor/Indonesia, 1992-2001 (Box 17, Folder 5-7)
    - El Salvador, 1983-1990 (Box 18, Folder 1-4)
    - Global Warming, 2004-2005 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Grenada, 1984-1990 (Box 20, Folder 2-3)
    - Grenada -- Phyllis Coard, 1988-2002 (Box 20, Folder 4-5, Box 21, Folder 1-2)
    - Guatemala, 1988-1997 (Box 21, Folder 3-6, Box 22, Box 23, Box 24, Folder 1-3, Box 87, Folder 4-5)
    - Guatemala (Contains Graphic Images), 1993-1994 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Guatemala -- Jennifer Harbury, 1994 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Guatemala -- Rigoberta Menchu Tum, 1992-1999 (Box 24, Folder 6, Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Haiti, 1993-1994 (Box 25, Folder 2-4)
    - Iraq, 1992 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Israel and Palestine, 1988-2002 (Box 26, Folder 6-7, Box 27, Box 28, Box 29, Box 86, Folder 2)
    - Israel and Palestine -- Palestinian Women Prisoners in Israel, 1992 (Box Shared Tamiment 084, Audiocassette 342.0001-342.0003)
    - Israel and Palestine -- Riyadh Za'Aq'q, 1996-1997 (Box 30, Folder 1-2)
    - Israel and Palestine -- Rula Abu Duhou, 1990-1997 (Box 30, Folder 3-5)
    - Korea, 1990-1993 (Box 31, Folder 1-5)
    - Malaysia, 1988-1994 (Box 31, Folder 7, Box 32, Folder 1-4)
    - Malaysia -- Benedict Topin, 1990-1992 (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - Malaysia -- Margaret John, 1996-2002 (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Missing Social Workers and Political Prisoners, 1977-1990 (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - Myanmar (formerly Burma), 1985-1994 (Box 1, Folder 5-6, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Folder 1-4)
    - Nicaragua, 1992-1993 (Box 36, Folder 2, Box 87, Folder 6)
    - Peru, 1994 (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - Philippines, 1983-2003 (Box 36, Folder 4-5, Box 37, Box 38, Box 39, Box 40)
    - Philippines, 1989-2003 (Box 41, Box 42, Folder 1-4, Box 87, Folder 7-9)
    - Philippines -- Evelyn Balais-Serrano, 1984-1985, 1992-1993 (Box 42, Folder 5)
    - Phyllis Grunauer, 2000 (Box 43, Folder 1)
    - Resist Magazine, 1989 (Box 43, Folder 2)
    - Shirley Gunn & Judy Taguiwalo Project, 1992 (Box 43, Folder 3-4)
    - Singapore, 1988-1994 (Box 43, Folder 5-6, Box 44, Folder 1)
    - South Africa, 1984-1991 (Box 44, Folder 2-4, Box 45, Box 87, Folder 10)
    - South Africa -- Shirley Gunn, 1990-2002 (Box 46, Folder 1-2)
    - South Africa -- Winnie Mandela, 1991 (Box 46, Folder 3)
    - Sri Lanka, 1993-1994 (Box 46, Folder 4-5)
    - SSEU Local 371 Membership, 1996 (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Sudan -- Child Soldiers, 2001 (Box 46, Folder 6)
    - United States -- Death Penalty, 1999-2001 (Box 46, Folder 7, Box 47, Folder 1-2)
    - United States -- Deportation and Undocumented Immigrants, 1977-2000 (Box 47, Folder 3-4)
    - United States -- Female Prisoners, 1988-1989 (Box 47, Folder 5-6, Box 87, Folder 11)
    - United States -- Glen Remer-Thamert, 1988-1990 (Box 48, Folder 1-2)
    - United States -- Joe Doherty, 1990-1992 (Box 48, Folder 3)
    - United States -- Lynne Stewart, 2002-2003 (Box 48, Folder 4-5)
    - United States -- Marilyn Montenegro, 2000 (Box 48, Folder 6)
    - United States -- MOVE Prisoners, 1996 (Box 49, Folder 1)
    - United States -- Mumia Abu-Jamal, 1995-2000 (Box 49, Folder 2-6, Box 50, Folder 1-5, Box 87, Folder 12-14)
    - United States -- Native American Rights and Leonard Peltier, 1986-2002 (Box 50, Folder 6, Box 51, Folder 1-2, Box 87, Folder 15)
    - United States -- North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) and General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT), 1992-1994 (Box 51, Folder 3-5, Box 52, Box 87, Folder 16)
    - United States -- Olga Gonzalez, 1996-1997 (Box 53, Folder 1-5)
    - United States -- Political Prisoners, 1990-1991 (Box 53, Folder 6)
    - United States --Ruth Messenger, 1985 (Box 86, Folder 3)
    - United States -- Silvia Baraldini, 1994-1997 (Box 54, Folder 1)
    - United States -- Susan Rosenberg, 1999-2001 (Box 54, Folder 2)
    - Vietnam, 1994 (Box 54, Folder 3)
    - Vinnie Burrows, 1989 (Box 54, Folder 4)
    - Women for Racial and Economic Equality (WREE), 1991-1993 (Box 54, Folder 5)
    - Women's Rights, 1991-1992 (Box 54, Folder 6)
- Series II: Affiliated Human Rights and Social Work Organizations, 1974-2005; 1985-2002; 10 Linear Feet in 14 manuscript boxes, 1 flat box, and 2 oversized flat boxes
  This series focuses upon the activities of human rights and social worker organizations that were affiliated with CIHRI and Ruth Wilson, or were of interest to Wilson as demonstrated by her collection of their informational materials.
  The majority of this series is focused upon the National Association of Social Workers (NASW) and International Federation of Social Workers (IFSW) and includes correspondence and petitions; election and conference materials; topic files focused upon human rights violations in specific countries and against specific individuals; and administrative documents including membership lists, newsletters, and memorandums. Due to the large volume of materials related to the NASW and IFSW, it is likely Wilson was a member of these organizations.
  In addition to NASW and IFSW, the activities and interests of organizations including Asia Watch, Amnesty International, the Bertha Capen Reynolds Society, Human Rights Watch, Oxfam America, and the United Nations are also represented in this series. Materials related to these and other organizations include booklets, flyers, and brochures; conference agendas, petitions, speeches, press statements; newspaper clippings and articles about human rights violations; factbooks and research materials focused on countries, the types of human rights issues in those countries, and specific individuals; and published government reports about human rights conditions globally.
  Together, these materials reflect the diversity of human rights and social work organizations that were active between 1974-2005; the types of groups, geographic regions, and human rights violations these organizations advocated on behalf of; and the types of activities they engaged in.
  Materials have been arranged alphabetically by organization name.
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1985-1987 (Box 54, Folder 7)
  - American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) -- Death Penalty, 1996 (Box 54, Folder 8)
  - American Humanist Association, 2004 (Box 54, Folder 9)
  - Amnesty International, 1994 (Box 55, Folder 1)
  - Amnesty International -- Amnesty Action, 1993 (Box 88, Folder 1)
  - Amnesty International -- Asia, 1991-1993 (Box 55, Folder 2)
  - Amnesty International -- Burma/Myanmar, 1995-1996 (Box 55, Folder 3)
  - Amnesty International -- Colombia, 1994 (Box 55, Folder 4)
  - Amnesty International -- Death Penalty, 2001 (Box 55, Folder 5, Box 86, Folder 4)
  - Amnesty International -- Iran, 2002 (Box 55, Folder 6)
  - Amnesty International -- Israel and Palestine, 1988 (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - Amnesty International -- Mumia Abu-Jamal, 2000 (Box 55, Folder 7)
  - Amnesty International -- Pakistan, 1992 (Box 55, Folder 8)
  - Amnesty International -- South America, 1991-1993 (Box 55, Folder 9)
  - Asia Watch -- China, 1991-1993 (Box 55, Folder 10)
  - Asia Watch -- Committee of Human Rights Watch, 1990-1991 (Box 55, Folder 11)
  - Association for Women in Social Work, 1990 (Box 56, Folder 1)
  - Bertha Capen Reynolds Society, 1978-2000 (Box 56, Folder 2-5)
  - The Burma-American Fund, 1990-1992 (Box 56, Folder 6)
  - Canadian Association of Social Workers, 1991-1993 (Box 56, Folder 7)
  - Center for International Policy - "Promoting Central American Negotiations", 1991 (Box 56, Folder 8)
  - Human Rights Committee of South Africa, 1994 (Box 56, Folder 9, Box 86, Folder 6)
  - Human Rights Watch, 1990-1994 (Box 57, Folder 1-4)
  - Institute for Central American Development Studies, 1995 (Box 88, Folder 2)
  - International Action Center - Iraq, 2001 (Box 57, Folder 5)
  - International Association of Schools and Social Work (IASSW), 1974, 1988-1989 (Box 57, Folder 6)
  - International Committee for Peace and Reunification of Korea, 1989-1991 (Box 57, Folder 7)
  - International Federation of Social Workers (IFSW), 1985-2002 (Box 58, Folder 1-4, Box 88, Folder 3)
  - IFSW -- Conferences, 1994, 1996, 2000 (Box 58, Folder 5)
  - IFSW -- Evelyn Balais-Serrano Speech, 1994 (Box 58, Folder 6)